<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Working thoughts 💭🧑‍💻</title>
    <link>https://lukasz.dev/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Working thoughts 💭🧑‍💻</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.150.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>2013-2025 Lukasz Plotnicki</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 21:22:55 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://lukasz.dev/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why Now</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/why-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 21:22:55 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/why-now/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a while, huh!? I think my writing comes in waves.
This time what inspired me, was rediscovering a &lt;a href=&#34;https://hamvocke.com/&#34;&gt;blog of buddy of mine, Ham&lt;/a&gt;
and binge-reading the posts that I&amp;rsquo;ve missed in recent years. While reading it,
and seeing that Ham is not limiting himself only to technical bits, I started
thinking how much pleasure writing gives me&amp;hellip; So after re-dusting my
whole hugo+github setup (read: sinking few hours in updating it), I finally
got to press some keys to create a &lt;a href=&#34;https://lukasz.dev/now&#34;&gt;Now&lt;/a&gt; page - also inspired by
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hamvocke.com/now/&#34;&gt;Ham&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt; and the discovery of the concept of
a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nownownow.com/about&#34;&gt;now page&lt;/a&gt;. Go there to read about my current setup
and what is currently on my mind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Now</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 12:20:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/now/</guid>
      <description>This a living space where I describe what I&amp;#39;m currently looking into, what&amp;#39;s on my mind &amp;amp; working with (home office setup, dotfiles etc.)</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A change / next step</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/a_change/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 15:35:37 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/a_change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in 2013, I was building a &lt;a href=&#34;https://certain-registry.eu&#34;&gt;system&lt;/a&gt; to help
with pediatric kidney transplant research while also trying to write a PhD at the
same time. That split did not work out. I liked building the system and the team around
it way more than writing papers and the dissertation work itself. Still, it took me
a while though to actually acknowledge that. To allow myself to say: I like the one
thing more than the original goal. But finally I did and
decided to focus exactly on this: building tech, building teams, learning how
to do it better and to do a lot of that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Java Frameworks in 2020 ?</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/java-frameworks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 07:49:31 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/java-frameworks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Java/JVM ecosystem is extremely mature and vast. It comes with a palette of production-ready choices for libraries solving problems that we face developing all kinds of services: be it from logging/metrics to async messaging or access to all the major sql and nosql data stores. Add the big talent pool (Java is very often used as the programming language used during CS-courses)[&lt;a href=&#34;https://cacm.acm.org/blogs/blog-cacm/176450-python-is-now-the-most-popular-introductory-teaching-language-at-top-u-s-universities/fulltext&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;] and it&amp;rsquo;s no wonder that this particular language and ecosystem is on the top or among the top 5 in the programming language statistics [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tiobe.com/tiobe-index/&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;][&lt;a href=&#34;https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2019#technology&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My first UHK layout</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/uhk_setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 23:24:02 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/uhk_setup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I ordered the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ultimatehackingkeyboard.com&#34;&gt;UHK&lt;/a&gt; with the linux layout
as I thought that I will be moving towards a linux laptop as the main driver
for my work. Somehow this didn&amp;rsquo;t happen :confused: and therefore I ended up using the UHK
with a Mackbook Pro. Thus, I changed few settings and love my setup even more.
UHK is really a spectacular keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://lukasz.dev/media/keyboard.png&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I quickly decided to just align the &lt;strong&gt;Fn&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Ctrl&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Option&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Cmd&lt;/strong&gt;
key with the mac layout so that my mussle memory doesn&amp;rsquo;t suffer too much. This
also made me fell in love with the UHK agent: It&amp;rsquo;s just so easy to remap the
keys to your liking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using your yubikey as ssh key provider / Quick(est) guide</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/sshkey_yubikey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 21:36:52 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/sshkey_yubikey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I figured it&amp;rsquo;s time to write up the quickest guide about using the yubikey as
the source of your ssh key. This assumes that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have a yubikey and it&amp;rsquo;s in your usb port&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve configured gpg on you machine (I&amp;rsquo;m running gpg (GnuPG) 2.2.7)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re using the gpg-agent with enabled ssh support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;gpg --card-edit
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; admin
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; generate
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;enter the requested PIN&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; quit
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;And now you&amp;rsquo;re done. You can check if the new ssh key get pulled correctly from
your yubikey typing:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>why hugo?</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/why-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 21:44:11 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/why-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you can see looking at the frequency of my posts, I&amp;rsquo;m more of an occasional
writer. Therefore whenever I drag myself in front of my notebook, to write
something up I&amp;rsquo;m feeling like sharing, I should really not have any reason to
do something else instead. Sadly, although I was really happy with my
&lt;a href=&#34;http://octopress.org&#34;&gt;octopress&lt;/a&gt; setup, more than once
I found myself fighting the currently installed ruby versions and some
conflicts with the gems that octopress was requiring.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>bff</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2016/02/22/bff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2016/02/22/bff/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A while ago I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/bff-soundcloud&#34;&gt;ThoughtWorks insights post&lt;/a&gt; about the
&lt;strong&gt;Backends for frontends&lt;/strong&gt; pattern and the story behind its adaption at
&lt;a href=&#34;http://soundcloud.com&#34;&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;. It generated interesting discussions
and resulted also in some further content and I thought it would be good to
have a place with links to all this resources for the future reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/bff-soundcloud&#34;&gt;BFF @ SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt; - the original post talking about the pattern and journey towards it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://samnewman.io/patterns/architectural/bff/&#34;&gt;BFF pattern definition&lt;/a&gt; - comprehensive pattern definition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://softwareengineeringdaily.com/2016/02/04/moving-to-microservices-at-soundcloud-with-lukasz-plotnicki/&#34;&gt;Moving to Microservices at SoundCloud - Software Engineering Daily podcast&lt;/a&gt; - a podcast talking about microservices in gerneral, SoundCloud&amp;rsquo;s journey towards this style of architecture and usage of BFFs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/thoughtworks/bff-soundcloud&#34;&gt;BFF @ SoundCloud (podcast)&lt;/a&gt; - an interview about UI composition in a microservices world in general and the BFF pattern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>express testing</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2015/10/10/express-testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2015/10/10/express-testing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://lukasz.dev/media/test_pyramid.jpg&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

After we managed to set up our basic &lt;a href=&#34;https://lukasz.dev/blog/2015/08/04/bootstraping-a-node-dot-js-webapp/&#34;&gt;web application&lt;/a&gt;,
let&amp;rsquo;s get our
hands dirty writing some code. And as we want to do it in a test-driven
manner (&lt;a href=&#34;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/TestDrivenDevelopment.html&#34;&gt;TDD&lt;/a&gt;), we need
a proper test setup. This piece is all about our initial test pyramid. Test,
what? Yes, pyramid:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the base of the test automation pyramid is unit testing. Unit testing should
be the foundation of a solid test automation strategy and as such represents
the largest part of the pyramid. (&amp;hellip;) Automated user interface testing is
placed at the top of the test automation pyramid because we want to do as
little of it as possible. (&amp;hellip;) Testing through the user interface like this is
expensive and should be minimized. Although there are many test cases that need
to be invoked, not all need to be run through the user interface. And this is
where the service layer of the test automation pyramid comes in. - Mike Cohn &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mountaingoatsoftware.com/blog/the-forgotten-layer-of-the-test-automation-pyramid&#34;&gt;https://www.mountaingoatsoftware.com/blog/the-forgotten-layer-of-the-test-automation-pyramid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>bootstraping a node.js webapp</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2015/08/04/bootstraping-a-node-dot-js-webapp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2015/08/04/bootstraping-a-node-dot-js-webapp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Together with few friends we started building &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lplotni/pace&#34;&gt;pace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - a web application for
organizing and managing running events &amp;amp; competitions. We are a colorful bunch of people with different backgrounds, therefore we wanted to choose an approachable tech stack, as some of us wants also to learn one or two things about &lt;strong&gt;JavaScript&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;web applications&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;programming&lt;/strong&gt; in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, somebody suggested to write one thing or two, about our technology
decisions and accompany it with some &lt;em&gt;HowTo&lt;/em&gt; information. So here we are.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>build monitors</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2015/06/27/build-monitors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2015/06/27/build-monitors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my last four projects or so, the teams I worked with were always using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.go.cd/&#34;&gt;GO.CD&lt;/a&gt; as the CD tool of their
choosing. Although the pipeline state visualisation GO.CD comes with is quite nice, it still doesn&amp;rsquo;t cut it as a proper,
&lt;em&gt;obvious&lt;/em&gt; build monitor enabling everybody in the team to quickly recognize what is the pipeline status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://lukasz.dev/media/burstah_example.png&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            Burstah in action
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore first &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lplotni/cidar&#34;&gt;cidar&lt;/a&gt;, a simple sinatra based build monitor, has been born. I quickly discovered
that sinatra and especially the nokogiri dependency, doesn&amp;rsquo;t make it easy to use e.g. a Raspberry Pi as the monitor hardware. So,
having the liberty, I decided to re-implement everything in JavaScript using node.js &amp;amp; express. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lplotni/burstah&#34;&gt;Burstah&lt;/a&gt;
, my second attempt at the ultimative build monitor, has been born :grin:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>scoopcamp hackathon</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2013/09/14/scoopcamp-hackathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2013/09/14/scoopcamp-hackathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last Thursday I was a part of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://scoopcamp.de/hackathon/&#34;&gt;Scoopcamp hackathon&lt;/a&gt; and it was so great that I just couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist to write down some of my thoughts about it. Our team &lt;strong&gt;ThoughtWorks and friends&lt;/strong&gt; a colorful mix of journalists, students and developers had a rough idea for a modern - more &lt;strong&gt;agile&lt;/strong&gt; - journalism, where the journalist reporting about an ongoing event writes the background story and live updates from his perspective, but can also incorporate content written by the readers who create their own streams representing their own take on the particular event. Being able to see which stream/entry is getting most likes (=feedback), he/she can quickly react and focus on the currently favorite perspective. During a quick brainstorming we came up with the name: &lt;strong&gt;LiquidPub&lt;/strong&gt; (for liquid publishing) and started defining the first user stories.
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://lukasz.dev/media/liquidpub_screenshot.png&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            Our app
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
 To be able to deliver something within less than a day of coding, we went with Ruby on Rails. This gave me the opportunity to finally try out Rails and learn it a bit by pairing with some experienced Ruby/Rails devs. The application itself has been deployed on heroku and being ThoughtWorks we built and deployed it after each push to our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thoughtworks/liquid-pub&#34;&gt;github repo&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.snap-ci.com/&#34;&gt;snap-ci&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/ContinuousDelivery.html&#34;&gt;continuous delivery&lt;/a&gt; FTW!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>gwt part i</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2013/06/15/gwt-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2013/06/15/gwt-part-i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in 2009 I became the job to design and start realizing a quite large web application for a health care research project. I took some time, sat down and thought about the technology stack, I would like to use to build it. As we wanted to have an RIA and I already had some experience with GWT, we quickly decided to use it. Since then four years have passed and we are about to release the 2.0 version of our system. During this time, the whole team learned a lot about GWT, its advantages and also some disadvantages, and I thought it would be useful to write some of them up. This part is about the &lt;strong&gt;status quo&lt;/strong&gt;, in the second part I will try to write about a GWT setup I would go for, when starting the project today - so if you have any hints in this regard, please feel free to leave a comment, I would definitely appreciate it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>setting up ...</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2013/05/14/setting-up-dot-dot-dot/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2013/05/14/setting-up-dot-dot-dot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like this moment, when you have a big smile on your face, because you&amp;rsquo;re just stunned how well things are working and how simple the set-up process was. &lt;a href=&#34;http://octopress.org&#34;&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt; is just amazing. &lt;strong&gt;Period&lt;/strong&gt;. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t heard about it and you&amp;rsquo;re thinking to start a blog or migrate one, then you should definitely check it out. To put it simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Octopress is a framework designed by Brandon Mathis for Jekyll, the blog aware static site generator powering Github Pages. To start blogging with Jekyll, you have to write your own HTML templates, CSS, Javascripts and set up your configuration. But with Octopress All of that is already taken care of. Simply clone or fork Octopress, install dependencies and the theme, and you&amp;rsquo;re set. - Brandon Mathis &lt;a href=&#34;http://octopress.org/blog/2011/07/23/octopress-20-surfaces/&#34;&gt;http://octopress.org/blog/2011/07/23/octopress-20-surfaces/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>hello world</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2013/05/09/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/blog/2013/05/09/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had this idea to create my own blog since like forever but always convinced myself that it will be either too time consuming or all the topics I would like to write about, are already well described, so what&amp;rsquo;s the point &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, I had also too many moments, when I thought - wait, you already had this problem/issue/idea&amp;hellip; What was the solution? Where did you find it?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Few words about me</title>
      <link>https://lukasz.dev/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lukasz.dev/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Lukasz (he/him) and I really like creating products together with
awesome teams. The roles that I play vary from a staff engineer, tech lead, engineering manager or head of engineering as I enjoy jumping between the IC and management tracks.
Whenever I can, I get my hands dirty with Java, Kotlin and &lt;del&gt;Java&lt;/del&gt;TypeScript with a proper amount of terraform for the infrastructure. Ex-&lt;a href=&#34;https://thoughtworks.com&#34;&gt;Thoughtworks&lt;/a&gt;, currently building things at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.air-up.com&#34;&gt;air up&lt;/a&gt; 💦‍️.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
