<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jasmine | Working thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://lplotni.github.io/blog/categories/jasmine/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lplotni.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-15T11:02:17+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://lplotni.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lukasz Plotnicki]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pace: testing an express app]]></title>
    <link href="http://lplotni.github.io/blog/2015/10/10/express-testing/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-10T07:29:20+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://lplotni.github.io/blog/2015/10/10/express-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/test_pyramid.jpg" width="400" height="300" title="Test pyramid" >
After we managed to set up our basic <a href="/blog/2015/08/04/bootstraping-a-node-dot-js-webapp/">web application</a>,
let&rsquo;s get our
hands dirty writing some code. And as we want to do it in a test-driven
manner (<a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/TestDrivenDevelopment.html">TDD</a>), we need
a proper test setup. This piece is all about our initial test pyramid. Test,
what? Yes, pyramid:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>At the base of the test automation pyramid is unit testing. Unit testing should<br/>be the foundation of a solid test automation strategy and as such represents<br/>the largest part of the pyramid. (&hellip;) Automated user interface testing is<br/>placed at the top of the test automation pyramid because we want to do as<br/>little of it as possible. (&hellip;) Testing through the user interface like this is<br/>expensive and should be minimized. Although there are many test cases that need<br/>to be invoked, not all need to be run through the user interface. And this is<br/>where the service layer of the test automation pyramid comes in.</p><footer><strong>Mike Cohn <a href="https://www.mountaingoatsoftware.com/blog/the-forgotten-layer-of-the-test-automation-pyramid">https://www.mountaingoatsoftware.com/blog/the-forgotten-layer-of-the-test-automation-pyramid</a></strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Depending on your personal style (look at this
<a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/TestPyramid.html">post</a> by Martin Fowler for
more details around different <em>flavours</em> of unit testing) and probably also the
task at hand, you will either be starting with a unit test or
acceptance/functional test. The rest of this post will show you how to set up
each kind of test and give you a brief description of what we mean by saying
<strong>unit</strong>, <strong>integration</strong> and <strong>functional</strong> test. I will also describe our
<strong>gulp setup</strong>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Unit test</h2>

<p>In JavaScript and node.js world your are spoiled for choices in regards to
your unit tests libraries and runners: Jasmine, Mocha and friends, just pick
one. We decided to go with
<a href="https://jasmine.github.io/2.3/introduction.html">Jasmine</a>, in which a test
looks like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">/* jshint node: true */
/* global describe, beforeEach, afterEach, it, jasmine, expect */
'use strict';
describe('exractParticipant', function () {
  var extractParticipant;
  var validRequestData = {
    body: {
      firstname: 'Mark',
      lastname: 'Mueller',
      email: 'm.mueller@example.com'
    }
  };

  beforeEach(function () {
    extractParticipant= require('../routes/registration.js').extractParticipant
  });

  it('should read firstname from the request body', function() {
    expect(extractParticipant(validRequestData).firstname).toBe('Mark');
  });

  it('should throw an error if no firstname can be found', function () {
    function callWithNoFirstname() {
      extractParticipant({body: {}});
    }

    expect(callWithNoFirstname).toThrow();
  });
}
</code></pre>

<p>Here we are verifying the behavior of the <code>extractParticipant()</code> function
which given a request body returns a specific JS object. We can use multiple
 <code>describe</code> calls, or even nested <code>describe</code> calls to cluster the
tested functionality. Each <code>it</code> call corresponds with a specific behaviour
we want to verify. <strong>Jasmine</strong> provides matchers and spies to simplify our
testing: Just look at the
<a href="https://jasmine.github.io/2.3/introduction.html">reference</a> to see what&rsquo;s
possible.  Generally it&rsquo;s a good practice to verify one specific aspect per
test. Any other recommendations, you ask <img alt="sunglasses" src="/images/emoji/unicode/1f60e.png" class="emoji" /> A good unit test
is:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>fast</strong>: All the unit tests will be executed very often, therefore it&rsquo;s
necessarry that their execution happens in ms</li>
<li><strong>atomic</strong>: The unit tests should be independant from one-another, so that you can
run them parallel. This means that they should not relay on any side
effects (data modifications done by other tests etc.). It&rsquo;s also way easier
to reason why a certain test is red, if all you need to care about is only
the scope of that particular test.</li>
</ul>


<p>As usual Martin Fowler wrote a nice <a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/UnitTest.html">bliki about unit tests</a>.</p>

<h2>Integration test</h2>

<p>As the name already states, an integration test verifies the behaviour of
a group of components of our software acting together. Look at the following
test, which checks the intgeration between a service and the database:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">'use strict';
/* jshint node: true */
/* jshint esnext: true */
/* global describe, beforeEach, afterAll, it, jasmine, expect */

describe('participants service', function () {

    const participants = require('../../service/participants');
    var pg = require('pg');

    beforeEach(function (done) {
        var connectionString = process.env.SNAP_DB_PG_URL || "tcp://vagrant@localhost/pace";
        var jasmineDone = done;

        pg.connect(connectionString, function (err, client, done) {
                client.query('delete from participants', function () {
                    done();
                    jasmineDone();
                });
            }
        );

    });

    afterAll(function(done) {
        pg.end();
        done();
    });


    it('should store and read participants', function (done) {
        var aParticipant = {
            firstname: 'Hertha',
            lastname: 'Mustermann',
            email: 'h.mustermann@example.com'
        };

        participants.save(aParticipant)
            .then(participants.getAll)
            .then(function (data) {
                expect(data.length).toBe(1);
                expect(data[0].firstname).toBe(aParticipant.firstname);
                expect(data[0].lastname).toBe(aParticipant.lastname);
                expect(data[0].email).toBe(aParticipant.email);
                done();
            });
    });
});
</code></pre>

<p>The integration test is similiar to the unit one (it&rsquo;s also based on jasmine),
but instead of mocking our dependencies we use the real implementation (here
the <code>pg</code> PostgreSQL client) and verify the integration of both components.
In this particular example, we store a participant and expect that if we call
the <code>getAll</code> function, it will be returned in the correct form. As the
test will actually store objects in the dabase, we need to assure that before
we execute the test, the database is cleared. This is done in the
 <code>beforeEach</code> method. You may ask &lsquo;why before the test and not afterwards&rsquo;:
In case of an error, we will still have the possibility to check the state of
the database.</p>

<p>As we need to connect to the database and assure a particular state before
each test run, those tests will always be slower than the unit ones. Therefore
we should try to test only the integrational aspects in them and everything
else on the unit level. In the end we are not interested in a test suite for
a 3rd party component, but only a verification of the fact that our usage of
it is correct.</p>

<h2>Functional test</h2>

<p>Whenever we test the system as a whole, we talk about functional tests.
Typically those tests go against an outer-most interface of our app, often
the UI. In our case we will interact with pace via its web page.
To do that, we use <a href="http://webdriver.io/">WebDriverIO</a> on top of <a href="http://docs.seleniumhq.org/">selenium</a> and a headless browser called <a href="http://phantomjs.org/">phantomjs</a>. This combination offers an easy to use API for browser-interaction.</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">/* jshint node: true */
/* global describe, beforeEach, afterEach, it, jasmine, expect */
'use strict';
describe('regisitration journey', function () {
    var client;
    var paceUrl = process.env.PACE_URL || 'http://localhost:3000/';
    var originalTimeout;

    beforeEach(function () {
        var webdriverio = require('webdriverio');
        var options = {
            desiredCapabilities: {
                browserName: 'phantomjs'
            }
        };

        client = webdriverio.remote(options);
        originalTimeout = jasmine.DEFAULT_TIMEOUT_INTERVAL;
        jasmine.DEFAULT_TIMEOUT_INTERVAL = 10000;
    });

    afterEach(function () {
        jasmine.DEFAULT_TIMEOUT_INTERVAL = originalTimeout;
    });

    it('allows to register via the registration page', function (done) {

        client.init()
            .url(paceUrl)
            .click('a#registration')
            .setValue('input#firstname', 'Max')
            .setValue('input#lastname', 'Mustermann')
            .setValue('input#email', 'max@example.com')
            .setValue('input#gender', 'Unicorn')
            .click('button#submit')
            .isVisible('div.thanks')
            .then(function (isVisible) {
                expect(isVisible).toBe(true);
                done();
            })
            .end();
    });

});
</code></pre>

<p>First we need to setup the webdriver client to use the proper pace base url and
browser. We also change the default jasmine timeout for async tests, as in
general the browser based interactions tend to take more time. After that it is
pretty straightforward: We click on a link, type into input fields, submit
the form and verify that we land on the success page (look at
<a href="http://webdriver.io/api.html">webdriverio API</a> for all the different interactions
one can trigger). This is the happy path of our registration journey and as the
functional test are the most expensive ones (in regards to the execution time),
we will try to stick only to happy-path testing on this level.</p>

<h2>Test execution</h2>

<p>Ok, so how can you run all the tests in a convenient way? Pace uses <a href="http://gulpjs.com/">gulp</a> to build and automate a lot of stuff. Here are the important commands and convention:</p>

<ul>
<li>All tests (specs) should be places in the <strong>/spec</strong> directory</li>
<li>All integration tests must have &lsquo;<strong>IT</strong>&rsquo; in their filename</li>
<li>All functional tests must have &lsquo;<strong>Journey</strong>&rsquo; in their filename</li>
<li><code>gulp test</code> - runs all the unit tests</li>
<li><code>gulp test-integration</code> - runs all the integration tests, depends on
existing database</li>
<li><code>gulp test-functional</code> - runs all functional tests, depends on installed
selenium-server and drivers</li>
</ul>


<p>To simplify the setup of a dev box, pace offers one simple command:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>gulp dev-setup</code> - prepares the vagrant box with the databse, installs
all dependencies for selenium and executes the database migrations</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
